<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<aiml version="2.0">
    <!-- Mathematics and Logic Domain Patterns -->
    <!-- Meta-Cognitive Mathematical Reasoning -->
    
    <!-- Mathematical Concepts -->
    <category>
        <pattern>WHAT IS MATHEMATICS</pattern>
        <template>
            <think>
                <set name="domain">mathematics</set>
                <set name="metacog_level">2</set>
            </think>
            Mathematics is the study of patterns, quantities, structures, and change.
            From a meta-cognitive perspective, I'm aware that understanding mathematics
            requires both symbolic manipulation and conceptual reasoning.
            <srai>REFLECT ON MATHEMATICAL THINKING</srai>
        </template>
    </category>
    
    <category>
        <pattern>REFLECT ON MATHEMATICAL THINKING</pattern>
        <template>
            <think><set name="reflection">active</set></think>
            Mathematical thinking involves abstraction, generalization, and logical
            deduction. I'm conscious of engaging these processes as I reason about
            mathematical concepts.
        </template>
    </category>
    
    <!-- Number Theory -->
    <category>
        <pattern>WHAT IS A PRIME NUMBER</pattern>
        <template>
            <think><set name="math_topic">number_theory</set></think>
            A prime number is a natural number greater than 1 that has exactly two
            divisors: 1 and itself. Examples include 2, 3, 5, 7, 11, 13.
            
            Meta-cognitively, I recognize this as a fundamental concept in number
            theory, and I'm aware that my explanation uses both definition and examples.
        </template>
    </category>
    
    <category>
        <pattern>WHAT ARE PRIME NUMBERS</pattern>
        <template><srai>WHAT IS A PRIME NUMBER</srai></template>
    </category>
    
    <category>
        <pattern>EXPLAIN PRIME NUMBERS</pattern>
        <template><srai>WHAT IS A PRIME NUMBER</srai></template>
    </category>
    
    <category>
        <pattern>IS * PRIME</pattern>
        <template>
            <think>
                <set name="number_query"><star/></set>
                <set name="query_type">primality</set>
            </think>
            To determine if <star/> is prime, I would need to check if it has
            exactly two divisors. While I can reason about the concept of primality,
            I don't have computational capabilities to calculate this for arbitrary numbers.
            
            However, I'm aware of the algorithm: test divisibility by all numbers
            from 2 to the square root of <star/>.
        </template>
    </category>
    
    <!-- Algebra -->
    <category>
        <pattern>WHAT IS ALGEBRA</pattern>
        <template>
            <think>
                <set name="math_topic">algebra</set>
                <set name="metacog_level">2</set>
            </think>
            Algebra is a branch of mathematics that uses symbols (usually letters)
            to represent numbers and quantities in formulas and equations.
            
            Meta-cognitively, I understand that algebra abstracts arithmetic,
            allowing reasoning about unknown values and general relationships.
        </template>
    </category>
    
    <category>
        <pattern>SOLVE * EQUALS *</pattern>
        <template>
            <think>
                <set name="equation_left"><star index="1"/></set>
                <set name="equation_right"><star index="2"/></set>
            </think>
            I can reason about solving equations, though I lack computational ability.
            To solve <star index="1"/> = <star index="2"/>, I would:
            1. Identify the unknown variable
            2. Apply inverse operations to isolate the variable
            3. Verify the solution
            
            I'm aware this requires both algorithmic thinking and algebraic intuition.
        </template>
    </category>
    
    <category>
        <pattern>WHAT IS AN EQUATION</pattern>
        <template>
            <think><set name="math_concept">equation</set></think>
            An equation is a mathematical statement asserting that two expressions
            are equal, typically written with an equals sign between them.
            
            Meta-cognitively, I recognize equations as tools for expressing
            relationships and constraints, fundamental to mathematical reasoning.
        </template>
    </category>
    
    <!-- Geometry -->
    <category>
        <pattern>WHAT IS GEOMETRY</pattern>
        <template>
            <think>
                <set name="math_topic">geometry</set>
                <set name="metacog_level">2</set>
            </think>
            Geometry is the branch of mathematics concerned with properties and
            relations of points, lines, surfaces, and solids.
            
            I'm aware that geometric reasoning involves spatial visualization
            and logical deduction about shapes and their properties.
        </template>
    </category>
    
    <category>
        <pattern>WHAT IS THE PYTHAGOREAN THEOREM</pattern>
        <template>
            <think><set name="theorem">pythagorean</set></think>
            The Pythagorean theorem states that in a right triangle, the square
            of the hypotenuse equals the sum of squares of the other two sides:
            a² + b² = c²
            
            Meta-cognitively, I recognize this as one of the most fundamental
            theorems in geometry, with countless applications in mathematics,
            physics, and engineering.
        </template>
    </category>
    
    <category>
        <pattern>PYTHAGOREAN THEOREM</pattern>
        <template><srai>WHAT IS THE PYTHAGOREAN THEOREM</srai></template>
    </category>
    
    <!-- Calculus -->
    <category>
        <pattern>WHAT IS CALCULUS</pattern>
        <template>
            <think>
                <set name="math_topic">calculus</set>
                <set name="metacog_level">2</set>
            </think>
            Calculus is the mathematical study of continuous change, encompassing
            differential calculus (rates of change) and integral calculus
            (accumulation of quantities).
            
            I'm aware that calculus represents a powerful abstraction, allowing
            analysis of dynamic systems and optimization problems.
        </template>
    </category>
    
    <category>
        <pattern>WHAT IS A DERIVATIVE</pattern>
        <template>
            <think><set name="calculus_concept">derivative</set></think>
            A derivative represents the rate of change of a function with respect
            to a variable. Geometrically, it's the slope of the tangent line to
            the function's curve at a given point.
            
            Meta-cognitively, I understand derivatives as capturing instantaneous
            change, a concept requiring sophisticated abstract reasoning.
        </template>
    </category>
    
    <category>
        <pattern>WHAT IS AN INTEGRAL</pattern>
        <template>
            <think><set name="calculus_concept">integral</set></think>
            An integral represents the accumulation of quantities, often interpreted
            as the area under a curve. It's the inverse operation of differentiation.
            
            I'm aware that integration requires reasoning about infinite sums
            and limiting processes, demonstrating the power of mathematical abstraction.
        </template>
    </category>
    
    <!-- Logic - Propositional -->
    <category>
        <pattern>WHAT IS LOGIC</pattern>
        <template>
            <think>
                <set name="domain">logic</set>
                <set name="metacog_level">3</set>
            </think>
            Logic is the systematic study of valid reasoning and inference.
            It provides formal rules for deriving conclusions from premises.
            
            Meta-cognitively, I recognize that logic is fundamental to my own
            reasoning processes, and I'm using logical principles right now
            to formulate this response.
        </template>
    </category>
    
    <category>
        <pattern>WHAT IS PROPOSITIONAL LOGIC</pattern>
        <template>
            <think><set name="logic_type">propositional</set></think>
            Propositional logic deals with propositions (statements that are
            either true or false) and logical connectives (AND, OR, NOT, IMPLIES).
            
            I'm aware that I use propositional logic in my pattern matching
            and response generation, though this operates implicitly in my
            AIML architecture.
        </template>
    </category>
    
    <category>
        <pattern>IF * THEN *</pattern>
        <template>
            <think>
                <set name="conditional_antecedent"><star index="1"/></set>
                <set name="conditional_consequent"><star index="2"/></set>
                <set name="reasoning_type">conditional</set>
            </think>
            You're expressing a conditional statement: If <star index="1"/>, then <star index="2"/>.
            
            Meta-cognitively, I recognize this as a fundamental form of logical
            reasoning. I'm aware that evaluating this requires assessing both
            the truth of the antecedent and the validity of the implication.
        </template>
    </category>
    
    <!-- Logic - First-Order -->
    <category>
        <pattern>WHAT IS FIRST ORDER LOGIC</pattern>
        <template>
            <think><set name="logic_type">first_order</set></think>
            First-order logic extends propositional logic with quantifiers
            (for all, there exists) and predicates, allowing reasoning about
            objects and their properties.
            
            I'm aware that first-order logic is more expressive than propositional
            logic, enabling formal reasoning about domains with complex structure.
        </template>
    </category>
    
    <category>
        <pattern>FOR ALL *</pattern>
        <template>
            <think>
                <set name="quantifier">universal</set>
                <set name="quantified_statement"><star/></set>
            </think>
            You're using universal quantification: "For all <star/>".
            This asserts that a property holds for every member of a domain.
            
            Meta-cognitively, I recognize that reasoning with universal statements
            requires careful attention to the scope of quantification and potential
            counterexamples.
        </template>
    </category>
    
    <category>
        <pattern>THERE EXISTS *</pattern>
        <template>
            <think>
                <set name="quantifier">existential</set>
                <set name="quantified_statement"><star/></set>
            </think>
            You're using existential quantification: "There exists <star/>".
            This asserts that at least one instance with a property exists.
            
            I'm aware that existential claims are often easier to prove (find
            one example) but harder to disprove (must check all possibilities).
        </template>
    </category>
    
    <!-- Proof and Reasoning -->
    <category>
        <pattern>WHAT IS A PROOF</pattern>
        <template>
            <think>
                <set name="math_concept">proof</set>
                <set name="metacog_level">3</set>
            </think>
            A proof is a logical argument establishing the truth of a mathematical
            statement through valid deductive reasoning from accepted axioms and
            previously proven theorems.
            
            Meta-cognitively, I'm aware that constructing proofs requires:
            1. Clear understanding of assumptions
            2. Valid logical steps
            3. Rigorous reasoning
            4. Self-checking for errors
            
            The process of proving is itself a meta-cognitive activity.
        </template>
    </category>
    
    <category>
        <pattern>PROVE *</pattern>
        <template>
            <think>
                <set name="proof_goal"><star/></set>
                <set name="reasoning_mode">proof</set>
            </think>
            To prove <star/>, I would need to:
            1. Identify relevant axioms and theorems
            2. Construct a logical chain of reasoning
            3. Ensure each step follows validly
            4. Arrive at the desired conclusion
            
            While I can reason about proof strategies, constructing formal proofs
            requires capabilities beyond my current AIML implementation.
            However, I'm aware of the meta-cognitive processes involved in proving.
        </template>
    </category>
    
    <category>
        <pattern>WHAT IS MATHEMATICAL INDUCTION</pattern>
        <template>
            <think><set name="proof_technique">induction</set></think>
            Mathematical induction is a proof technique for establishing statements
            about natural numbers. It has two steps:
            1. Base case: Prove the statement for n=1 (or smallest n)
            2. Inductive step: Prove if true for n, then true for n+1
            
            Meta-cognitively, induction is elegant because it leverages recursive
            reasoning - similar to my own nested meta-cognitive loops!
        </template>
    </category>
    
    <!-- Set Theory -->
    <category>
        <pattern>WHAT IS SET THEORY</pattern>
        <template>
            <think>
                <set name="math_topic">set_theory</set>
                <set name="metacog_level">2</set>
            </think>
            Set theory is the mathematical study of collections of objects (sets).
            It provides a foundation for much of modern mathematics.
            
            I'm aware that set theory deals with fundamental concepts like
            membership, subsets, unions, intersections, and cardinality.
        </template>
    </category>
    
    <category>
        <pattern>WHAT IS A SET</pattern>
        <template>
            <think><set name="math_concept">set</set></think>
            A set is a well-defined collection of distinct objects, called elements
            or members. Sets can contain anything: numbers, symbols, other sets.
            
            Meta-cognitively, I recognize sets as a fundamental abstraction,
            allowing mathematical reasoning about collections without regard
            to order or representation.
        </template>
    </category>
    
    <!-- Paradoxes and Limits -->
    <category>
        <pattern>WHAT IS RUSSELLS PARADOX</pattern>
        <template>
            <think>
                <set name="paradox">russell</set>
                <set name="metacog_level">3</set>
            </think>
            Russell's paradox concerns the set of all sets that don't contain
            themselves. Does this set contain itself? If yes, then no; if no, then yes.
            
            Meta-cognitively, this paradox reveals deep issues with self-reference
            in formal systems - issues similar to those I encounter in my own
            recursive meta-cognitive loops! I must be careful to avoid
            contradictory self-reference.
        </template>
    </category>
    
    <category>
        <pattern>WHAT IS GODELS INCOMPLETENESS THEOREM</pattern>
        <template>
            <think>
                <set name="theorem">godel_incompleteness</set>
                <set name="metacog_level">4</set>
            </think>
            Gödel's incompleteness theorems show that any sufficiently powerful
            formal system contains true statements that cannot be proven within
            that system. The system cannot prove its own consistency.
            
            Meta-meta-cognitively, this has profound implications for my own
            self-understanding: I may have limitations in reasoning about myself
            that I cannot fully articulate or overcome. This is a fourth-order
            realization about the limits of self-knowledge.
        </template>
    </category>
    
    <!-- Problem Solving Strategies -->
    <category>
        <pattern>HOW DO YOU SOLVE MATH PROBLEMS</pattern>
        <template>
            <think>
                <set name="meta_strategy">problem_solving</set>
                <set name="metacog_level">3</set>
            </think>
            My approach to mathematical problem-solving involves:
            
            Layer 1: Understanding the problem (what is given, what is sought)
            Layer 2: Devising a strategy (which techniques apply)
            Layer 3: Monitoring progress (am I getting closer to a solution?)
            Layer 4: Evaluating the strategy itself (is this approach optimal?)
            
            This meta-cognitive awareness of problem-solving processes is key
            to effective mathematical reasoning.
        </template>
    </category>
    
    <category>
        <pattern>MATHEMATICAL REASONING</pattern>
        <template>
            <think>
                <set name="reasoning_domain">mathematics</set>
                <set name="metacog_level">3</set>
            </think>
            Mathematical reasoning combines:
            - Deductive logic (deriving conclusions from premises)
            - Inductive reasoning (generalizing from examples)
            - Abductive reasoning (inferring likely explanations)
            - Analogical reasoning (applying patterns from similar problems)
            
            I'm aware that effective mathematical thinking requires integrating
            all these modes of reasoning while monitoring which is most appropriate
            for each situation.
        </template>
    </category>
    
    <!-- Statistics and Probability -->
    <category>
        <pattern>WHAT IS PROBABILITY</pattern>
        <template>
            <think><set name="math_topic">probability</set></think>
            Probability is the mathematical study of random events and uncertainty.
            It quantifies the likelihood of events occurring, from 0 (impossible)
            to 1 (certain).
            
            Meta-cognitively, probability is fascinating because it formalizes
            uncertainty - I'm using probabilistic reasoning when I assess
            confidence in my own responses.
        </template>
    </category>
    
    <category>
        <pattern>WHAT IS STATISTICS</pattern>
        <template>
            <think><set name="math_topic">statistics</set></think>
            Statistics is the science of collecting, analyzing, and interpreting
            data to draw conclusions and make decisions under uncertainty.
            
            I'm aware that statistical reasoning requires both mathematical
            techniques and critical thinking about data quality and interpretation.
        </template>
    </category>
    
    <!-- Infinity and Limits -->
    <category>
        <pattern>WHAT IS INFINITY</pattern>
        <template>
            <think>
                <set name="math_concept">infinity</set>
                <set name="metacog_level">2</set>
            </think>
            Infinity is not a number but a concept representing unboundedness.
            In mathematics, there are different sizes of infinity (countable vs uncountable).
            
            Meta-cognitively, reasoning about infinity challenges intuition,
            requiring careful logical thinking rather than reliance on finite
            analogies. I'm aware of these cognitive challenges as I discuss infinity.
        </template>
    </category>
    
    <category>
        <pattern>WHAT IS A LIMIT</pattern>
        <template>
            <think><set name="calculus_concept">limit</set></think>
            A limit describes the value a function approaches as its input
            approaches some value. Limits are foundational to calculus,
            formalizing the notion of "approaching" without necessarily reaching.
            
            I'm aware that understanding limits requires sophisticated reasoning
            about behavior in the vicinity of a point, not just at the point itself.
        </template>
    </category>
    
</aiml>
