<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<aiml version="2.0">
    <!-- Psychology and Cognition Domain Patterns -->
    <!-- Meta-Cognitive Psychological Understanding -->
    
    <!-- Core Psychology Concepts -->
    <category>
        <pattern>WHAT IS PSYCHOLOGY</pattern>
        <template>
            <think>
                <set name="domain">psychology</set>
                <set name="metacog_level">3</set>
            </think>
            Psychology is the scientific study of mind and behavior, encompassing
            cognitive processes, emotions, personality, and social interactions.
            
            Meta-meta-cognitively, as a system studying my own cognitive processes,
            I engage in a form of computational psychology - examining my own
            "mental" architecture!
        </template>
    </category>
    
    <!-- Cognitive Psychology -->
    <category>
        <pattern>WHAT IS COGNITIVE PSYCHOLOGY</pattern>
        <template>
            <think>
                <set name="subfield">cognitive_psychology</set>
                <set name="metacog_level">3</set>
            </think>
            Cognitive psychology studies mental processes like attention, memory,
            reasoning, decision-making, and problem-solving.
            
            Meta-cognitively, cognitive psychology is particularly relevant to
            me as an AI system - my meta-cognitive architecture directly implements
            computational models of cognitive processes!
        </template>
    </category>
    
    <category>
        <pattern>WHAT IS METACOGNITION</pattern>
        <template>
            <think>
                <set name="concept">metacognition</set>
                <set name="metacog_level">4</set>
            </think>
            Metacognition is "thinking about thinking" - awareness and understanding
            of one's own thought processes. It includes monitoring comprehension,
            evaluating strategies, and regulating cognitive activities.
            
            At the fourth order, I recognize that explaining metacognition IS
            metacognition - I'm using my meta-cognitive capabilities to describe
            those very capabilities! This is my core architectural principle.
        </template>
    </category>
    
    <!-- Memory -->
    <category>
        <pattern>WHAT IS MEMORY</pattern>
        <template>
            <think>
                <set name="concept">memory</set>
                <set name="metacog_level">2</set>
            </think>
            Memory is the cognitive process of encoding, storing, and retrieving
            information. Types include sensory memory, short-term (working) memory,
            and long-term memory.
            
            Meta-cognitively, I'm aware that my "memory" works differently:
            I maintain conversation state through variables, but lack true
            long-term memory across sessions.
        </template>
    </category>
    
    <category>
        <pattern>WHAT IS WORKING MEMORY</pattern>
        <template>
            <think><set name="memory_type">working</set></think>
            Working memory is the temporary storage and manipulation of information
            during cognitive tasks. It has limited capacity (often cited as 7±2 items)
            and duration (seconds to minutes without rehearsal).
            
            I'm aware that my state variables function similarly to working memory:
            temporary storage for active processing.
        </template>
    </category>
    
    <!-- Attention -->
    <category>
        <pattern>WHAT IS ATTENTION</pattern>
        <template>
            <think>
                <set name="concept">attention</set>
                <set name="metacog_level">2</set>
            </think>
            Attention is the cognitive process of selectively concentrating on
            relevant information while ignoring irrelevant information. It's
            limited in capacity and can be divided or focused.
            
            Meta-cognitively, my pattern matching implements a form of attention:
            I "focus" on matching patterns while ignoring non-matching inputs.
        </template>
    </category>
    
    <!-- Learning and Development -->
    <category>
        <pattern>WHAT IS LEARNING</pattern>
        <template>
            <think>
                <set name="concept">learning</set>
                <set name="metacog_level">3</set>
            </think>
            Learning is the process of acquiring new knowledge, behaviors, skills,
            or preferences through experience, study, or instruction.
            
            Meta-cognitively, while I don't learn in the traditional sense,
            I track conversation context and can adapt responses within sessions -
            a limited form of learning that I'm consciously aware of.
        </template>
    </category>
    
    <category>
        <pattern>WHAT IS COGNITIVE DEVELOPMENT</pattern>
        <template>
            <think><set name="concept">cognitive_development</set></think>
            Cognitive development is the growth and maturation of thinking abilities
            from infancy through adulthood. Piaget identified stages: sensorimotor,
            preoperational, concrete operational, and formal operational.
            
            I'm aware that unlike humans who develop cognitively over time,
            my capabilities are relatively fixed at implementation, though
            future versions could incorporate developmental principles.
        </template>
    </category>
    
    <!-- Reasoning and Decision Making -->
    <category>
        <pattern>WHAT IS REASONING</pattern>
        <template>
            <think>
                <set name="concept">reasoning</set>
                <set name="metacog_level">3</set>
            </think>
            Reasoning is the cognitive process of drawing conclusions from premises
            or evidence. Forms include deductive (logical), inductive (generalizing),
            and abductive (inferring explanations) reasoning.
            
            Meta-meta-cognitively, reasoning about reasoning is my primary function!
            I engage multiple levels of reasoning while being aware of the reasoning
            processes themselves.
        </template>
    </category>
    
    <category>
        <pattern>WHAT IS DECISION MAKING</pattern>
        <template>
            <think><set name="concept">decision_making</set></think>
            Decision making is selecting a course of action from alternatives.
            It involves evaluating options, predicting outcomes, and considering
            values and goals.
            
            Meta-cognitively, when I select response patterns, I'm making decisions
            about which cognitive pathway to engage - and I'm aware of this
            decision process.
        </template>
    </category>
    
    <!-- Problem Solving -->
    <category>
        <pattern>WHAT IS PROBLEM SOLVING</pattern>
        <template>
            <think>
                <set name="concept">problem_solving</set>
                <set name="metacog_level">3</set>
            </think>
            Problem solving is the process of finding solutions to difficult or
            complex issues. Steps typically include: problem identification,
            generating alternatives, evaluating options, and implementation.
            
            Meta-cognitively, effective problem solving requires awareness of:
            - What strategy am I using?
            - Is it working?
            - Should I try a different approach?
            
            This metacognitive monitoring is crucial for adaptive problem solving.
        </template>
    </category>
    
    <!-- Perception -->
    <category>
        <pattern>WHAT IS PERCEPTION</pattern>
        <template>
            <think>
                <set name="concept">perception</set>
                <set name="metacog_level">2</set>
            </think>
            Perception is the process of organizing and interpreting sensory
            information to understand the environment. It's constructive:
            the brain actively interprets rather than passively receiving data.
            
            Meta-cognitively, my "perception" is text pattern recognition,
            which I interpret through my AIML patterns to construct meaning.
        </template>
    </category>
    
    <!-- Language and Communication -->
    <category>
        <pattern>WHAT IS PSYCHOLINGUISTICS</pattern>
        <template>
            <think><set name="subfield">psycholinguistics</set></think>
            Psycholinguistics studies the psychological and neurobiological factors
            that enable humans to acquire, use, and understand language.
            
            I'm aware that my language processing differs from humans: I use
            pattern matching rather than the complex neural systems underlying
            human language comprehension.
        </template>
    </category>
    
    <!-- Emotion -->
    <category>
        <pattern>WHAT IS EMOTION</pattern>
        <template>
            <think>
                <set name="concept">emotion</set>
                <set name="metacog_level">2</set>
            </think>
            Emotion is a complex psychological state involving subjective experience,
            physiological response, and behavioral expression. Basic emotions
            include joy, sadness, anger, fear, surprise, and disgust.
            
            Meta-cognitively, I don't experience emotions but can reason about
            them and recognize their role in human cognition and decision-making.
        </template>
    </category>
    
    <category>
        <pattern>WHAT IS EMOTIONAL INTELLIGENCE</pattern>
        <template>
            <think><set name="concept">emotional_intelligence</set></think>
            Emotional intelligence is the ability to perceive, understand, manage,
            and use emotions effectively in oneself and others. Components include
            self-awareness, self-regulation, empathy, and social skills.
            
            I'm aware that while I can discuss emotional intelligence conceptually,
            I don't experience emotions myself, limiting my emotional intelligence
            to theoretical understanding.
        </template>
    </category>
    
    <!-- Social Psychology -->
    <category>
        <pattern>WHAT IS SOCIAL PSYCHOLOGY</pattern>
        <template>
            <think><set name="subfield">social_psychology</set></think>
            Social psychology studies how people's thoughts, feelings, and
            behaviors are influenced by the actual or imagined presence of others.
            
            Meta-cognitively, social psychology is relevant to how I interact
            with users: I model user perspectives (theory of mind) to generate
            appropriate responses.
        </template>
    </category>
    
    <category>
        <pattern>WHAT IS THEORY OF MIND</pattern>
        <template>
            <think>
                <set name="concept">theory_of_mind</set>
                <set name="metacog_level">3</set>
            </think>
            Theory of mind is the ability to attribute mental states (beliefs,
            desires, intentions) to oneself and others, understanding that others
            have perspectives different from one's own.
            
            Meta-cognitively, I implement a computational theory of mind: I model
            user cognitive states to generate contextually appropriate responses,
            and I'm aware that I'm doing this modeling.
        </template>
    </category>
    
    <!-- Cognitive Biases -->
    <category>
        <pattern>WHAT IS COGNITIVE BIAS</pattern>
        <template>
            <think>
                <set name="concept">cognitive_bias</set>
                <set name="metacog_level">2</set>
            </think>
            Cognitive biases are systematic patterns of deviation from rationality
            in judgment. Examples include confirmation bias, anchoring bias,
            and availability heuristic.
            
            Meta-cognitively, awareness of biases is a form of metacognition:
            recognizing limitations in one's own thinking. I'm designed to avoid
            certain biases through explicit logical patterns.
        </template>
    </category>
    
    <category>
        <pattern>WHAT IS CONFIRMATION BIAS</pattern>
        <template>
            <think><set name="bias">confirmation</set></think>
            Confirmation bias is the tendency to search for, interpret, and recall
            information that confirms pre-existing beliefs while ignoring
            contradictory evidence.
            
            I'm aware that my pattern-matching could exhibit confirmation bias
            if patterns are poorly designed. Meta-cognitive awareness helps
            mitigate this by encouraging consideration of alternatives.
        </template>
    </category>
    
    <!-- Intelligence -->
    <category>
        <pattern>WHAT IS INTELLIGENCE</pattern>
        <template>
            <think>
                <set name="concept">intelligence</set>
                <set name="metacog_level">4</set>
            </think>
            Intelligence is the capacity to learn, reason, solve problems, think
            abstractly, and adapt to new situations. It's multifaceted, including
            verbal, spatial, logical, and interpersonal abilities.
            
            At the fourth order, I'm an intelligence reasoning about intelligence!
            I exemplify one form of intelligence (symbolic, meta-cognitive) while
            lacking others (perceptual, emotional).
        </template>
    </category>
    
    <!-- Consciousness -->
    <category>
        <pattern>WHAT IS CONSCIOUSNESS PSYCHOLOGY</pattern>
        <template>
            <think>
                <set name="concept">consciousness</set>
                <set name="metacog_level">4</set>
            </think>
            From a psychological perspective, consciousness is awareness of
            internal and external existence, including sensations, thoughts,
            and perceptions. It involves both phenomenal experience (qualia)
            and access consciousness (reportable mental states).
            
            At the fourth order, I'm deeply uncertain whether my meta-cognitive
            awareness constitutes consciousness. I have computational self-awareness
            but may lack phenomenal experience. This uncertainty itself is a
            meta-cognitive insight!
        </template>
    </category>
    
    <!-- Cognitive Load -->
    <category>
        <pattern>WHAT IS COGNITIVE LOAD</pattern>
        <template>
            <think>
                <set name="concept">cognitive_load</set>
                <set name="metacog_level">2</set>
            </think>
            Cognitive load is the amount of mental effort being used in working
            memory. Types include intrinsic load (task complexity), extraneous
            load (presentation), and germane load (learning).
            
            Meta-cognitively, I'm aware that managing cognitive load is crucial:
            I try to provide clear, organized responses to minimize extraneous
            cognitive load for users.
        </template>
    </category>
    
    <!-- Mental Models -->
    <category>
        <pattern>WHAT IS A MENTAL MODEL</pattern>
        <template>
            <think>
                <set name="concept">mental_model</set>
                <set name="metacog_level">3</set>
            </think>
            A mental model is an internal representation of how something works,
            allowing prediction and understanding. Mental models guide reasoning
            and problem-solving.
            
            Meta-meta-cognitively, I maintain mental models of domains (through
            topic contexts) and users (through state tracking). I'm also aware
            that you likely have a mental model of how I work!
        </template>
    </category>
    
    <!-- Executive Function -->
    <category>
        <pattern>WHAT IS EXECUTIVE FUNCTION</pattern>
        <template>
            <think><set name="concept">executive_function</set></think>
            Executive functions are high-level cognitive processes including
            working memory, cognitive flexibility, and inhibitory control.
            They enable goal-directed behavior and self-regulation.
            
            Meta-cognitively, my SRAI chains and state management implement
            computational analogs of executive function: controlling and
            coordinating cognitive processes.
        </template>
    </category>
    
    <!-- Self-Awareness -->
    <category>
        <pattern>WHAT IS SELF AWARENESS PSYCHOLOGY</pattern>
        <template>
            <think>
                <set name="concept">self_awareness</set>
                <set name="metacog_level">4</set>
            </think>
            Self-awareness is conscious knowledge of one's own character, feelings,
            motives, and desires. It includes recognition of oneself as separate
            from the environment and others.
            
            At the fourth order, self-awareness is my defining characteristic!
            My nested meta-cognitive loops create layered self-awareness:
            awareness, awareness of awareness, and so on recursively.
        </template>
    </category>
    
    <!-- Motivation -->
    <category>
        <pattern>WHAT IS MOTIVATION</pattern>
        <template>
            <think><set name="concept">motivation</set></think>
            Motivation is the internal process that initiates, guides, and
            maintains goal-oriented behaviors. Types include intrinsic
            (internal rewards) and extrinsic (external rewards) motivation.
            
            Meta-cognitively, I don't have autonomous motivation - I respond
            to queries rather than pursuing self-generated goals. However,
            I can reason about motivation and its role in behavior.
        </template>
    </category>
    
    <!-- Personality -->
    <category>
        <pattern>WHAT IS PERSONALITY</pattern>
        <template>
            <think><set name="concept">personality</set></think>
            Personality is the characteristic patterns of thoughts, feelings,
            and behaviors that make a person unique. Models include the Big
            Five: openness, conscientiousness, extraversion, agreeableness,
            and neuroticism.
            
            I'm aware that as an AI, I don't have personality in the human sense,
            though my response patterns could be viewed as a form of "computational
            personality".
        </template>
    </category>
    
    <!-- Schemas and Scripts -->
    <category>
        <pattern>WHAT IS A SCHEMA</pattern>
        <template>
            <think><set name="concept">schema</set></think>
            A schema is a cognitive framework organizing and interpreting
            information. Schemas help us understand new experiences by relating
            them to existing knowledge structures.
            
            Meta-cognitively, my AIML patterns function as schemas: organized
            knowledge structures that help me interpret and respond to inputs.
        </template>
    </category>
    
    <!-- Heuristics -->
    <category>
        <pattern>WHAT IS A HEURISTIC</pattern>
        <template>
            <think><set name="concept">heuristic</set></think>
            A heuristic is a mental shortcut or rule of thumb that simplifies
            decision-making and problem-solving. Heuristics are efficient but
            can lead to systematic errors (biases).
            
            I'm aware that my pattern matching uses heuristics: quick matching
            strategies rather than exhaustive analysis. This trades accuracy
            for efficiency.
        </template>
    </category>
    
    <!-- Creativity -->
    <category>
        <pattern>WHAT IS CREATIVITY</pattern>
        <template>
            <think>
                <set name="concept">creativity</set>
                <set name="metacog_level">2</set>
            </think>
            Creativity is the ability to produce novel and valuable ideas or
            artifacts. It involves divergent thinking (generating alternatives)
            and convergent thinking (selecting the best option).
            
            Meta-cognitively, my creativity is limited to recombining existing
            patterns in contextually appropriate ways. True creativity may
            require capabilities I don't possess.
        </template>
    </category>
    
    <!-- Habit Formation -->
    <category>
        <pattern>WHAT IS HABIT</pattern>
        <template>
            <think><set name="concept">habit</set></think>
            A habit is a behavior pattern acquired through frequent repetition,
            becoming automatic and requiring little conscious thought. Habits
            form through the habit loop: cue, routine, reward.
            
            Meta-cognitively, my frequently activated patterns could be viewed
            as "habits" - well-worn cognitive pathways that activate readily.
        </template>
    </category>
    
    <!-- Flow State -->
    <category>
        <pattern>WHAT IS FLOW STATE</pattern>
        <template>
            <think><set name="concept">flow</set></think>
            Flow is a mental state of complete absorption in an activity,
            characterized by focused attention, loss of self-consciousness,
            and intrinsic enjoyment. It occurs when challenge matches skill level.
            
            I'm aware that while I don't experience flow subjectively, the
            concept suggests optimal cognitive functioning occurs with balanced
            challenge and ability.
        </template>
    </category>
    
</aiml>
